Guide to the Austin Strong Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Austin Strong papers
1899-1951
YCAL MSS 619
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
7
(15 boxes)
The Austin Strong Papers contain correspondence, theater scripts, artwork, notebooks, diaries, sketchbooks, scrapbooks, photographs, photograph albums, printed material, and professional and personal papers. The papers primarily document Strong's professional work as a playwright, stage designer, theater producer, author, artist, and landscape architect. A small amount of material documents his work as a volunteer air raid warden in the 1940s.
Strong, Austin, 1881-1952
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Serendipity Books on the Adele Gutman Nathan Theatrical Collection Fund, 1996.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Austin Strong (1881-1952)
Austin Strong, American playwright, stage designer, theater producer, author, artist, and landscape architect. Strong was born in San Francisco on April 18, 1881 and grew up in Hawaii and Samoa, where he lived with his step-grandfather, Robert Louis Stevenson. Austin attended Wellington College in New Zealand from 1895 to 1898. He married and settled with his wife, Mary, in Nantucket, where he was well regarded for his preservation initiatives and yearly production of the Nantucket Follies. His plays include The Little Father of the Wilderness (1906), The Toymaker of Nuremberg (1907), The Pied Piper (1908), A Good Little Devil (1913), The Dragon's Claw (1914), Bunny (1916), Three Wise Fools (1918), Seventh Heaven (1922), Drums of Oude (1927), and A Play Without a Name (1928). Several of Strong's plays also became films. He died in Nantucket on September 17, 1952.
Scope and Contents
The Austin Strong Papers contain correspondence, theater scripts, artwork, notebooks, diaries, sketchbooks, scrapbooks, photographs, photograph albums, printed material, and professional and personal papers. The papers primarily document Strong's professional work as a playwright, stage designer, theater producer, author, artist, and landscape architect. A small amount of material documents his work as a volunteer air raid warden in the 1940s.
Arrangement
Organized into six series: I. Correspondence, 1905-1948. II. Scripts, 1903-1928. III. Artwork, 1903-1926. IV. Notebooks and Diaries, 1899-1947. V. Scrapbooks and Photographs, 1899-1951. VI. Other Papers, 1907-1946.
Air raid wardens -- United States; Dramatists, American -- 20th Century; Artists -- United States; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Landscape architects -- United States; Set designers -- United States; World War, 1939-1945 -- United States; Architectural drawings (visual works); Drawings (visual works); Photographs; Photograph albums; Scrapbooks; Air raid wardens -- United States; Artists -- United States; Authors -- United States -- 20th Century; Dramatists -- United States -- 20th Century; Landscape architects -- United States -- 20th Century; Set designers -- United States -- 20th Century; Strong, Austin, 1881-1952
- Correspondence, 1905-1948; Series I; 0.42; (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Vendor list is filed at the front of Box 1.
  - Correspondence filed in alphabetized file folders, 1912-1928 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    Approximately 85 letters to Strong with approximately 20 replies. Contains theater correspondence and business matters. Correspondents include actors and producers. Accompanied by mimeograph of cast list of The Toymaker of Nuremburg.
  - Belasco, David, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Regards production of And What Happened Then? and includes letters from Percy Jordan and Western Union telegraphs. Most letters are written on Belasco Theatre letterhead.
  - Boucicault, Dion, 1905-1906 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Regards producing Drums of Oude and written on Duke of York's letterhead.
  - Osbourne, Lloyd, 1905, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Regards seeking renewed collaboration on a play.
  - Letters from Carl Brandt and Houghton Mifflin; letter from Strong to Gertrude Stern, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Includes copies of "Rochaubeau: A commemoration by the Congress of the United States of America of the services of the French Auxiliary forces in the War of Independence, 1907" and "Note: sur le general Baron Friedrich Wilhelm von Steuben, 1794"
  - Letter from Hugh Walpole to Strong on the production of Seventh Heaven by Strong at the Booth Theatre, 1922 November 3 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Scripts, 1903-1928; Series II; 2.3; (3 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Organized into two subseries: Scripts by Austin Strong and Scripts by Others
  - Scripts by Austin Strong
    Typescripts of plays written by Strong, as maintained by Strong.
    - Bunny, bound typescript, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - The Dancing Master, manuscript drafts, 1904 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Drums of Oude, various versions, 1918, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 10-13)
    - Little Father of the Wilderness, printed version, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - My Lord of the Road, manuscript drafts, undated (Box 2, Folder 15-17)
    - The Perry Melodrama, manuscript draft, 1904 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Seventh Heaven, various versions, 1922 (Box 2, Folder 19-21)
    - Three Wise Fools, printed versions, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 22-24)
    - The Toymaker of Nuremburg, various versions, 1910, 1921 (Box 2, Folder 25-26)
    - When Fortune Flatters, manuscript drafts, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
      Includes empty notebooks
  - Scripts by Others
    All scripts by others are bound composite typescripts with portions of printed scripts mounted on the pages. Many contain handwritten and typescript notes by Strong. Strong was likely involved with the production or stage design of each.
    - Broadway by Philip Dunning and George Abbott, 1927 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Coquette by George Abbott and Ann Preston Bridgers, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Craig's Wife by George Kelly, 1926 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Exile by Martin Harvey, 1903 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Fata Morgan by Ernest Vajda, 1924 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - The Front Page by Ben Hecht and Charles MacArthur, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Hell-Bent Fer Heaven by Hatcher Hughes, undated (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Rain by John Colton, undated (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - The Second Mrs. Tangueray by Arthur W. Pinero, undated (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - The Show-Off by George Kelly, undated (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - The Silver Cord by Sidney Howard, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - What Every Woman Knows by J.M. Barrie, undated (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - What Price Glory, undated (Box 4, Folder 40)
- Artwork, 1903-1926; Series III
  Items are grouped together by size, format, or other physical characteristics.
  A detailed vendor list on the architectural and other drawings in boxes 11 and 12 is filed in box 11.
  - Eleven drawings for And What Happened Then?, four drawings for Microscopia and four related watercolors for background and stage scenery, 1908
  - Architectural and other drawings, 1903-1926, undated
    Includes some printed material
  - Architectural and other drawings, 1903-1926, undated
  - Sterner, Albert. Original lithograph: "Dinner Given to Walter Hapden by Some of His Fellow Players", 1919 January 12; Stored in: Oversize Box 13, folder 87
    Signed on verso by 22 dinner companions
  - Strong, Austin. Ink drawing of gargoyle eating a person, undated; Stored in: Oversize Box 15, folder 89
  - Kessler. Drawing of a figure resembling Father Brown, undated; Stored in: Oversize Box 15, folder 90
  - Sterner, Albert. Drawing inscribed "of and for his friend Harold Gould", 1923; Stored in: Oversize Box 13, folder 88
- Notebooks and Diaries, 1899-1947, undated; Series IV; 0.42; (1 box)
  - Notebooks, 1899 January 19-1901 September 10 (Box 5, Folder 41-53)
    Fourteen notebooks bound in cloth or wrappers. 20-60 pages each. Notebooks contain ideas for plays; sketches, drawings and colored pictures in each. Some inserted material. Sketch of Gillett as Sherlock Holmes. No. 4 has a playlet written out with finished colored stage drawings. New York, Pairs, Bruges, London, San Francisco.
    Most notebooks contain writings, notes, and sketches. Some contain mounted clippings.
  - "Idea Book", 1906-1909 (Box 5, Folder 54)
    Contains notes, sketches, ideas for plays and characters
  - "Puritan Play" notebook, undated (Box 5, Folder 55)
    Contains notes on Puritans for a possible play.
  - Diary, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - Sketchbook, undated (Box 5, Folder 57)
- Scrapbooks and Photographs, 1899-1951; Series V; 1.3; (4 boxes)
  - Scrapbooks
    - Unbound album sheets with autograph manuscript leaves, clippings and photographs mounted. Material regards Strong's commission to design, superintend and lay out the Auckland City Park, 1901-1902 (Box 6, Folder 58)
    - Contains postcards and clippings from England residence; a Churchill broadside, and several original drawings, 1903, undated
    - Contains clippings; reviews of his plays; poems to Strong from his father; clippings on Moonshine, Bunny, Napoleon, and Three Wise Fools, photographs and drawings (Box 7, Folder 59)
    - Contains 139 original drawings, most colored by Strong, usually for his own plays; My Lord of the Road, Pan, and Boomerang but also with clippings and a few photographs, 1907-1910 (Box 7, Folder 60)
    - Three-ring letter album, includes letters to Strong from various individuals, programs of plays and operas, sketches by Strong, clippings on Robert Louis Stevenson, photographs, and other ephemera, 1950-1951 (Box 8, Folder 61)
  - Photograph by J. Edward Graeme of Robert Louis Stevenson monument in San Francisco, circa 1932 (Box 8, Folder 62)
  - Photograph albums
    - Contains 362 photographs, nearly all are not captioned. Photographs depict Austin and Mary Strong, their travels, and other individuals, 1899, undated (Box 9, Folder 63)
    - Contains 21 photographs, including some snapshots and larger images of stage figures/actors, Strong, Sidney Howard, and Stewart Edward White, undated
  - Photograph of several individuals, with signatures on mat, 1919 July
- Other Papers, 1907-1946, undated; Series VI; 1; 1 box
  This series is arranged chronologically. Undated material is filed at the end of the series.
  Contains professional papers relating to Strong's theatrical productions, a short story he wrote entitled "All on a Winter's Night," his Drums of Oude 's inclusion as a service text by the War Department, and his work as a landscape architect. The series also contains personal papers, including financial papers; a printed version of an article his wife wrote in Nantucket's newspaper, The Cobble; and handbooks for his volunteer work as a New York City air warden.
  - Royalty statements for Strong's plays, 1907-1929 (Box 10, Folder 64)
    From Chas Frohman, Century Play, Samuel French, John Golden, and E. Marbury
  - Financial papers filed in alphabetized file folders, 1926-1929 (Box 10, Folder 65-73)
    Contains bills and receipts for goods, services, purchases, and dues for New York City and Nantucket homes. Also contains papers relating to dividends from investments, bills and receipts, and property and taxes.
  - Haymarket Theatre program for Rip Van Winkle by Strong, 1911 September 21 (Box 10, Folder 74)
  - Report of Military Entertainment Committee of the War Department's Commission on Training Camp Activities, 1918 (Box 10, Folder 75)
    Contains "Report of Austin Strong, Librarian of the Manuscript Division of the Department of Dramatic Activities Among the Soldiers"
  - The Cobble, newspaper from Nantucket, MA, 1919 September
    Contains a column written by Mary Strong
  - Nantucket Yacht Club Theatre program for the Nantucket Follies production of The Jolly Roger by Frederick Kitson Cowley and sketchbook, 1927 July, undated (Box 10, Folder 76)
  - Handbook for Air Raid Wardens, 1941 (Box 10, Folder 77)
  - "I Learned What It Means to Be Blind" by Austin Strong. Typescript, corrected and printed version in The Saturday Evening Post, 1944 April 20 (Box 10, Folder 77a)
  - "All on a Winter's Night" typescript draft, 1946 (Box 10, Folder 78)
  - Red Cross Handbook and course catalog, undated (Box 10, Folder 79)
  - Reports by Strong on Grant Park, Washington Park, D.C. Byer residence, and Marshfield Cedarhurst, undated (Box 10, Folder 80)
    These reports were written in Strong's capacity as a landscape architect.
- Oversize Material, 1.2; (4 boxes)
  - Eleven drawings for And What Happened Then?, four drawings for Microscopia and four related watercolors for background and stage scenery, 1908 (Box 11, Folder 81)
  - Architectural and other drawings, 1903-1926, undated (Box 11, Folder 82-83)
  - The Cobble, newspaper from Nantucket, MA, 1919 September (Box 11, Folder 84)
  - Contains postcards and clippings from England residence; a Churchill broadside, and several original drawings, 1903, undated (Box 12, Folder 85)
  - "I Learned What It Means to Be Blind" by Austin Strong. Typescript, printed version in The Saturday Evening Post, 1944 April 20 (Box 12, Folder 85a)
  - Contains 21 photographs, including some snapshots and larger images of stage figures/actors, Strong, Sidney Howard, and Stewart Edward White, undated (Box 12, Folder 86)
  - Sterner, Albert. Framed (double sided) original lithograph: "Dinner Given to Walter Hapden by Some of His Fellow Players", 1919 January 12 (Box 13, Folder 87)
    Signed on verso by 22 dinner companions, including Hampden, A. E. Thomas, Ernest Hunter, James Austin Wilder, Henry Stephenson, Arthur Goodrich, and Charles Hanson Towne.
  - Sterner, Albert. Framed drawing inscribed "of and for his friend Harold Gould", 1923 (Box 13, Folder 88)
  - Strong, Austin. Ink drawing of gargoyle eating a person, undated (Box 15, Folder 89)
  - Kessler. Drawing of a figure resembling Father Brown, undated (Box 15, Folder 90)
  - Photograph of several individuals, with signatures on mat, 1919 July (Box 15, Folder 91)
  - Architectural and other drawings, 1903-1926, undated (Box 14, Folder 92-96)